Finding aid for the Ben Pleasants papers, 1959-2013 LSC.2303
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ben Pleasants papers
1959-2013
1970-1985
UCLA Library Special Collections
Pleasants, Ben
Pleasants, Paula
LSC.2303
4 linear feet (4 boxes, 2 half-size boxes, 1 record carton, 5 shoeboxes)
0.5 linear feet (1 flat box)
10 audiovisual carriers (10 unprocessed audiocassettes)
This collection documents the activities, writings, and political opinions of Ben Pleasants. Pleasants was a Los Angeles-based writer, as well as a close friend of both Charles Bukowski and Steve Richmond, seminal figures in the Los Angeles "Meat School." He published works on John Fante, Kenneth Rexroth, James Laughlin, Kate Braverman, Marge Piercy, Budd Schulberg, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, and others. This collection spans from 1959 to 2013, and chronicles Pleasants' time in California as a poet, playwright, interviewer, and novelist.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paula Pleasants, 2016.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9979898383606533
Biographical History
Ben Pleasants was a Los Angeles-based writer. He was born on August 6, 1940 in Long Island, New York, and graduated from Hofstra University in 1962 before moving to California with his first wife. He began graduate studies in English at the University of California, Los Angeles in 1964.
While at UCLA, Pleasants became close friends with Steve Richmond and Charles Bukowski, seminal figures in the Los Angeles "Meat School" of poetry. Pleasants then joined the mimeograph revolution of the 1960s and 1970s. He was published in The Wormwood Review alongside contributors like Bertolt Brecht and Henry Miller, and was praised for his poetry collection, Airmail from Oblivion (1975).
Pleasants began working at the Los Angeles Times in 1967. His reputation as a reviewer led to his work being published by the Los Angeles Herald Examiner, the Los Angeles Free Press, and other Southern California periodicals. From 1978 to 1983, he conducted a series of interviews with John Fante, later collected by Beat Scene and 3:AM Magazine. His lauding of Fante helped spur a resurgence in the author's popularity, and cemented his semi-autobiographical novel Ask the Dust (1939) as a seminal work of Los Angeles literature.
In 1984, Pleasants left the LA Times over his attempt to review The Fateful Triangle, Noam Chomsky's book on US involvement in Middle East politics. Pleasants continued to write, publishing in periodicals such as the L.A. Free Press, L.A. Vanguard, L.A. Reader, Los Angeles Magazine, and Malibu Magazine. He also worked as a teacher for the Los Angeles United School District for thirty years.
Pleasants was also a noted playwright. His plays include Winter in Mongolia (1975), The Hemingway/Dos Passos Wars (1998), and Contentious Minds: The Mary McCarthy/Lillian Hellman Affair (2001). Late in life, Pleasants also turned to novels, publishing the sexually explicit tragicomedy Spearmint Leaves (2010) and The Victory of Defeat (2011), a thinly disguised account of Bukowski's activites during World War II.
In 2004, Pleasants published the memoir Visceral Bukowski: A Walk Through the Sniper Landscape of American Letters. Although critically praised, the book became controversial due to Pleasants' claims that Charles Bukowski harbored Nazi sympathies. Pleasants died of a heart attack on April 30, 2013 at age 72.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the writings, publishing attempts, and political opinions of Ben Pleasants, as well as his relationship with Steve Richmond and Charles Bukowski, seminal figures in the "Meat School" of the Los Angeles poetry scene.
The collection spans from 1960 to 2010, with the bulk of materials coming from 1970 to 1985, and is organized by subject or name, having no original order. In addition to manuscripts and correspondence, the collection contains a large number of publications featuring Pleasants' writing and interviews conducted by Pleasants.
Some of the significant organizations and topics represented in these files are: Charles Bukowski and the Meat School, the broader Los Angeles literary and drama scene, mimeograph publishing, John Fante and the Hollywood Ten, Nazi sympathies in America, and Stalin's atrocities as leader of the USSR. The collection documents Pleasants' provocative nature, anarchist sympathies, dismissal of PC culture, and free speech advocacy.
Materials are largely textual, comprising publications and personal and professional correspondence, as well as a large number of audio cassettes. Among other formats are photographs, CDs and DVDs.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Manuscripts (1961-2012)
Series 2: Interviews (1975-2013)
Series 3: Publications and Promotional Materials (1966-2013)
Series 4: Correspondence (1959-2010)
Series 5: Photos and Media (1961-2010)
Series 6: Biographical Materials (1966-2013)
No original order existed for this collection. Materials have been organized alphabetically by name or subject.
Pleasants, Ben -- Archives; Pleasants, Paula
- Manuscripts, 1961-2012
  Scope and Content
  Series is comprised of drafts of Pleasants' writing and assorted notes. Materials span 1961-2012 and include scripts, short story collections, poetry collections, and reviews.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series has been organized alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "1923" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Buddies" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Bukowski, Fante and Maserati Moon", 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Contentious Minds", 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Diary of an Ant", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Final Exams" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Gagaku from a Crack Motel" (S. Richmond), 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1-2, Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Goodman MacKay Project (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Half a Man" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Historical Materials, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "John Fante and the Hollywood Ten", 2010 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Nietzsche Among the Nightingales" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes, 1978-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poetry (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The Poisoning of Maxim Gorki", 2000s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Reagan's Worst Week", 2000s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reviews, 1980s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Short Stories (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "The Thrill of Victory and the Agony of Defeat", 2009 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Interviews, 1978-2013
  Series is comprised of interview recordings and transcripts by Pleasants, including conversations with John Fante, Dan Fante, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Marge Piercy, and Steve Richmond. Materials span 1975-2013 and include audio cassettes, CDs, and DVDs.
  This series has been organized alphabetically by name.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Ackerman (Page) (Box 4)
    One CD. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Ash (Monte), 1995 (Box 4)
    One CD and one audio cassette. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Barry (Julian) (1-2) (Box 4)
    Two audio cassettes. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Bottoms (Benjamin) Garden, 2012 (Box 4)
    One DVD. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Bottoms (Timothy), 2012 (Box 4)
  - Bottoms (Timothy and Bartholomew), 2011 (Box 4)
  - Bottoms (Timothy) Remembers His Brother Sam (Box 4)
  - Bottoms (Timothy) and Tamar Simon Hoffs, 2011 (Box 4)
  - Broadway (Box 4)
    One audio cassette. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Bunuel (Rafael) and John Prince, 2013 (Box 4)
  - Carduho (Jolyne) (1-2), 2009 (Box 4)
  - Chalfant (Edward) (1-3) (Box 4)
    Three audio cassettes. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Coleman (Stuart) (Box 4)
  - Couley (J.R.), 1977 (Box 4)
  - Cuodro (Luciano), 1986 (Box 4)
  - Davis (Brad) (Box 4)
  - Davison (Bruce) (1-2) (Box 4)
  - Dmytryk (Edward) (1-5), 1994 (Box 4)
    Five audio cassettes. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Fante (Dan) (1-2) (Box 5)
  - Ferlinghetti (Lawrence) (1-4), 1979 (Box 5)
    Four audio cassettes. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Honolulu (H.M.) (1-2) (Box 5)
  - Kriesel (Mark) (Box 5)
  - Keaton (Angela) (Box 5)
  - Kugelman (Jay), 2005 (Box 5)
  - Fante (John) (1-10), 1978-1981 (Box 5)
    Ten CDs. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Jacoulet (Errol) (Box 6)
  - Lackey (Bill) (1-2), 2009 (Box 6)
  - Majid, 2010 (Box 6)
  - McKay (Madeleine) (1-2), 2009 (Box 6)
  - Mortenson (Harold) (Box 6)
  - O'Neill (William) (Box 6)
  - Perreau (Eleanor and Gerald) (Box 6)
  - Pleasants' Mother, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Reed (Christine), 2010 (Box 6)
  - Richio (Sheena) (Box 6)
  - Richmond (Steve) (1-10), 2008-2009 (Box 6, Box 7)
    Four audio cassettes and six CDs. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Roth (Rex), 1976 (Box 6)
  - Schulberg (Budd) (1-2) (Box 7)
  - Sipos (Thomas), 2000s (Box 6)
  - Thompson (Woodrow) (1-2), 2009 (Box 6)
  - Transcripts: Fante (John), 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Transcripts: Kanon (Joseph), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Transcripts: Piercy (Marge), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Publications and Promotional Materials, 1966-2013
  Series is comprised primarily of published works, and promotional materials for Pleasants' plays. Materials span 1966-2013 and include issues of mimeograph publications like The Wormwood Review and Etc., plays and novels by Ben Pleasants, and poetry collections by Steve Richmond.
  This series has been organized alphabetically by author or publisher title.
  - Artist Retrospectives, 1981-2013 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Barry (Julian) Articles, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bowers Conference and Exhibition, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bukowski (Charles) Articles, 1978-2013 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Christmas in St. Mortiz" Short Story, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fante (John and Dan) Articles, 1979-2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Reviews and Programs, 1978-2014 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Richmond (Steve) Articles, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "This Can't Be Happening!" Articles, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Alley Cat Readings, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - American Literature and Criticism, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Bunuel (Rafael) and Ben Pleasants: Lines & Words, 2012 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Chinese Literature, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Crews (Judson): Nations and Peoples, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Etc. A Review of General Semantics, 1967-1973 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Frogpond, 1987-1989 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Haiku Review, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Locklin (Gerald): Locked In With Gerald Locklin, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Locklin (Gerald): Two Torch Singers, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Los Angeles Free Press, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Los Angeles Magazine, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Malibu Magazine, 2010-2011 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Modern Haiku, 1985-1988 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Nebula, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Pleasants (Ben): 53 Stations of the Tokaido, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Pleasants (Ben): Ghosts of Pumpkin Park, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Pleasants (Ben): The Hemingway/Dos Passos Wars, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Pleasants (Ben): Rexroth, Bukowski and the Politics of Literature, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Pleasants (Ben): Spearmint Leaves, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Pleasants (Ben): The Victory of Defeat, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Pleasants (Ben): Visceral Bukowski: Inside the Sniper Landscape of L.A. Writers, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Richmond (Steve): Earth Rose, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Richmond (Steve): Spinning Off Bukowski, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Richmond (Steve): Venice Jones, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Richmond (Steve): Wild Seed, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Small Pond, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Son of Poop, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - The Sunset Palms Hotel, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Tsebry (Ossip): Memories of a Makhnovist, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Tuatara, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Waves, 1972-1975 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - The Wormwood Review, 1969-1990 (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
- Correspondence, 1959-2010
  Series is comprised primarily of the personal and professional correspondence of Ben Pleasants. Materials span 1959-2010 and include letters between Steve Richmond and Charles Bukowski, as well.
  This series has been organized alphabetically by last name.
  - Ali (John) - Barry (Julian), 1974-2005 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Bartlett (Elizabeth), 1968-1979 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Beck (Thomas) - Bloom (Magdalena), 1971-2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Book Donations - Burns (George), 1970-2000 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Bukowski (Charles), 1977-1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Celebrities, 1973-1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Chalfant (Edward), 1962-1996 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Chomsky (Noam) - Conroy (Nancy), 1980-1997 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Davis (Jim), 1998-2002 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Douglass (Richard) - Eugdahl (Bernie), 1975-1990 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Fante Family, 1961-1983 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Ferlinghetti (Lawrence) - Frohman (Star), 1970-1993 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Gallagher (Dorothy), 1997-2000 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Kai-yu (Hsu) - Long (Robert), 1970-2007 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Malone (Marvin) - Maltz (Albert), 1973-1980 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Marks (F.) -O'Neill (Bill), 1976-2003 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - McIntosh and Otis, 1971-1978 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Neumann (Gerhard) - Pesin (Henry), 1975-1981 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Pleasants Family, 1972-2002 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Publishers' Letters, 1971-2010 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Redgrave (Vivian) - Reznikoff (Charles), 1965-1975 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Religious Censorship Study, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Richmond (Steve) (1-3), 1965-2009 (Box 10, Folder 23-24, Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Sandburg (Carl) - Snyder (Gary), 1959-1982 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Tidler (Charles), 1970-2004 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Turner (Roland) - Wolfe (Tom), 1969-2009 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Young (Harold), 1978-1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Photographs and Media, 1961-2010
  Series is comprised primarily of photographs and recordings of Pleasants' plays. Materials span 1961-2010 and include photos, audio cassettes, CDs, and DVDs.
  - "Contentious Minds" Photos, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Pleasants and Meat School Photos, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Richmond (Steve) Photos, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Visceral Bukowski" Photo Shoot, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Anthony and Cleopatra", 1961 (Box 12)
  - "Contentious Minds" Recording, 2000s (Box 12)
  - "Contentious Minds" Soundtrack, 2000s (Box 12)
  - Fante (Dan): Don Giovanni and Short Dog, 2000s (Box 12)
  - "A Girl Who Doesn't Know the Difference" (Box 12)
  - "The Hemingway/Dos Passos Wars" Recording, 2000s (Box 12)
    One CD. Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit..
  - "The Hemingway/Dos Passos Wars" Classical Music Trial, 2000s (Box 12)
  - "Hemingway Reads" (Box 12)
  - "Lenin in Love", 1990s (Box 12)
  - "Making the Play" (Box 12)
  - Pleasants (Ben): Poetry Reading, 1973 (Box 12)
  - "That Cold Day…" (Box 12)
- Biographical Materials, 1966-2013
  Series is comprised primarily of teaching certificates, memorial materials, and the Pleasants family tree. Materials span 1966-2013.
  This series has been organized alphabetically by subject.
  - Memorial Materials, 2013 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Pleasants Family, 1966-2011 (Box 8, Folder 3)